<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise concernynge the diuision betwene the spirytualtie and temporaltie</title>
            <author>Saint German, Christopher, 1460?-1540.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1532</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104701</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840434</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840434</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4938</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4938)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 145:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise concernynge the diuision betwene the spirytualtie and temporaltie</title>
                  <author>Saint German, Christopher, 1460?-1540.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>45, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In fletestrete next to sayncte Dunstones churche, by Robert Redman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1532?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Christopher Saint German.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4938:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4938:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶A tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiſe concernynge the diuiſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:4938:2"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>This lyttell booke declareth dyuers cauſes, wherby diuiſion hath ryſen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the ſpiritualtie and temporaltie: and partly ſheweth, howe they maye be brought to a vnite. And if they that may do mooſt good towarde the ſayd vnitie, wyll take the artycles of this treatiſe, as lyttel tytlinges to bring ſom weyghtier thynges to theyr mynde concernyng the ſame, and thanne by theyr wyſdomes wyll adde them here vnto: and (as they ſhall thynke neceſſarie) to ſee them all put in due execucion: I thynke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly that in ſhorte tyme they ſhall brynge this matter to good effecte, to the honoure of god, &amp; to the comon welth and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of all the kynges ſubiectes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4938:2"/>
            <head>¶Dyuers articles' whiche haue bene a ſpeciall cauſe of the diuiſion that is betwyxt the ſpiritualtie and the temporaltie in this realme.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The fyrſt Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho may remembre the ſtate of this realme nowe in theſe dayes, without great heuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſorow of herte? For there as in tymes paſt hath reygned charite, mekenes, concorde and peace reygneth nowe enuye, pryde, diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, and ſtryfe: &amp; that nat only betwene lay men and lay men, but alſo betwene religious and religious / and betwene preeſtes and relygyous, and that is yet more to be lamented, alſo betwene pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and preeſtes. Whiche diuiſion hath ben ſo vniuerſal / that it hath ben a great vnquietnes and a great breache of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie through all the realme: and part of it hathe ryſen by reaſon of a great ſingu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larite / that religious ꝑſons and preſtes haue hadde to theyr eſtate of lyuynge,
<pb facs="tcp:4938:3"/>
whereby many of theym haue thoughte theyr eſtate moſt perfyte before al other. And ſome of them haue thereby exalted them ſelfe in theyr owne ſyght ſo hyghe, that they haue ryſen into ſuche a gooſtly pryde, that they haue in maner diſday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and dyſpyſed other, that haue nat lyued in ſuche perfection as they thynke they doo. And of this hathe folowed, that ſome of theym haue hadde vnſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng wordes of the other, callynge them flatterers, diſſimulers, and hypocrites: And they haue called the other agayne proude perſons, couetous, vayne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous, and louers of worldely delytes, and ſuche other.</p>
               <p>¶And an other parte of this dyuyſyon hath ryſen by dyuerſities of opynyons, that haue ben vpon the auctorities, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and iuriſdiction of ſpirituall men amonge them ſelfe. And vpon theſe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſions ſome lay men haue in tyme paſt fauored the one parte, and ſome the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: whereby the people haue greately ben inquyeted. But I wote nat fully by what occaſyon it is, that nowe of late the great multytude of all the laye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4938:3"/>
haue founde defaute, as well at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes as relygyouſe / ſo ferfurthe, that it is nowe in maner noted through all the realme / that there is a greate dyuyſyon bytwene the ſpyritualtie and the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie. And verylie it is great pitie that ſuche a noyſe ſhulde ſprynge and goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode. And ſome alledge dyuers cauſes why it is ſo noyſed. Fyrſte they ſaye, that neyther preſtes nor religious kepe nat the perfeccyon of theyr ordre to the honour of god and good example of the people, as they ſhulde do: but that ſom of them procure theyr owne honour, and call it the honour of god, and rather co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet to haue rule ouer the people, than to profyte the people. And that ſome couet theyr bodyly eaſe and worldely welthe, in meate and drynke, and ſuche other / more than commenly any temporal man doeth. And that ſome ſerue god for a worldly laude, and to be magnified ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, more than for the pure loue of god. And ſome laye men ſaye farther / that though religious men haue varied with religious / and that ſom preſtes haue va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed alſo with religious in ſom pointes
<pb facs="tcp:4938:4"/>
concernynge the preeminence of theyr perfection, as is ſaid before: that yet in ſuche thynges as perteyne to the mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunce of the worldely honour of the churche and of ſpirituall men, whiche they call the honour of god, and in ſuch thynges as perteyn to the encrece of the riches of ſpiritual me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, religious or ſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, they ſay they agree all in one. And therfore they ſay, that all ſpiritual men, as to the multitude / be more diligent to enduce the people to ſuche thynges, as ſhall brynge riches to the churche, as to gyue money to trentals, and to founde chaunteries and obites, and to obteyne pardons, &amp; to go vpon pylgremages / and ſuche other: than they be to enduce them to the payment of theyr dettes / to make reſtitutions for ſuch wronges as they haue done / or to doo the werkes of mercye to theyr neyghboures, that be poore and nedye / and that ſomtyme be alſo in right extreme neceſſite.</p>
               <p>¶And for as moche as it is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſene / that amonge a great multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude there be many, that worke rather vpon wyll than vpon reaſon, And that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4938:4"/>
though they haue a good zele / yet many tymes they lacke good ordre and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, whiche is the mother of al vertue. Therfore ſome perſons thynkynge that worldely honoure and ryches lettethe greatly deuocion, ſo moche that as they thynke, they canne not ſtande togyther, haue holden opinion, that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the churche to haue any poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And ſome takynge a more meane waye therin, haue ſayde / that as they thynke, it is lawfull and alſo expedient, that the churche haue poſſeſſions: but they thynke / that the great haboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that is in the churche / doth great hurt / &amp; induceth in many of them, a loue to worldely thynges, and letteth and in maner ſtrangleth the loue of god.</p>
               <p>And therfore they thynke, that it were good to take awaye that is to moche / and to leue that is ſufficient. And ſome alſo, as of a policie to pulle ryches fro the churche, haue inueyed ayenſte all ſuche thynges as brynge ryches to the churche. And becauſe great ryches haue comme to the churche for prayenge for ſoules in purgatorie, haue by wordes
<pb facs="tcp:4938:5"/>
affyrmed that there is no purgatorie: And that grauntynge of pardons riſeth of couetyſe of the churche, and profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nat the people / and that pylgrema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be of no effecte / and that the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che may make no lawes / and ſuche other thynges / as foundynge of chaunteries, making of brotherhedes, and many mo. Wherein they ſhewe outwardly to ryſe agaynſt all the thynges before reherſed, and to diſpyſe them, and yet they knowe and beleue in theyr hertes, that all theſe thynges be of them ſelfe ryght good and profytable, as they be in dede, yf they were ordered as they ſhulde be. And ſomme perſones there be, that throughe grace fynde defaute onely at the abuſion and myſſe order of ſuche thynges, and ſpeke nothyng againſt the thinges ſelfe, neither of purgatory / pylgremages / ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vppe of ymages / or ſuche oher.</p>
               <p>For they knowe well, they be ordeyned of god, and that the myſorder ryſethe only of man for couetyſe, ſingularitie, or ſome other ſuche lyke defaute, throughe perſwaſyon and dyſceyte of the gooſtly enemye. And thoughe ſome men haue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4938:5"/>
myſtaken them ſelfe in the ſayd articles, yet dyuers other haue ſayd, that yf they had bene well and charitably handeled, they myghte haue benne refourmed, and paraduenture ſaued in bodye and in ſoule.</p>
               <p>¶And vpon al theſe maters there is ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen a great opynyon in the people, in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner vniuerſally, that in punyſſhyng and corrections all theſe perſones before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed ſhulde haue lyke punyſſhemente, yf ſpyrytuall men myght haue free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye in that behalfe. And that ſpyrytuall men wolde, yf they coulde: as well put them to ſcilence / that ſpeke ayenſt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſyon or diſordre of ſuche thynges, as be before reherſed / as them that ſpeke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yenſt the thynge ſelfe. And many other murmours &amp; grudges beſyde theſe that be before reherſed, be amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, mo than I can reherſe now: but yet aboue all other, me thynketh that it is mooſt to be lamented and ſorowed / that ſpyrytuall men / knowynge theſe grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and murmuracions among the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, and knowynge alſo that many laye men haue opinion / that a great occaſion
<pb facs="tcp:4938:6"/>
therof ryſeth by ſpyrytual men / and that they do no more to appeaſe them ne to ordre them ſelfe in no other maner for the appeaſynge of them, than they do.</p>
               <p>For al that they do therin moſt commen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly is this: they take it, that they that fynde defaute at ſuche abuſions and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordre, loue no preeſtes: and therfore they eſteme that they doo of malyce all that they do, to diſtroye the churche, and to haue theyr goodes and poſſeſſions them ſelfe: And therfore they thynke it a good dede to ſe theym punyſſhed, ſo that they ſhall not be able to brynge theyr malyce to effecte. And therfore haue they punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed many perſons, which moch people haue iuged them to do vpon will, and of no loue vnto the people. And though ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual men are bound in this caſe, for ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſyng of theſe opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che be ſo dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous as wel to ſpirituall men, as to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall men / that many ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſtonde in great peril therby, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reforme them ſelfe, and to leue and auoyde all thynges, that gyue occaſyon to the people ſo to offende, that maye by charitie be omytted and lefte / but alſo to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4938:6"/>
faſt, praye / were the heare / gyue almes, and to doo other good dedes for them ſelfe and for the people, cryenge conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to our lorde, that theſe diuiſions may ceaſſe, and that peace and concord may come agayne into the worlde: yet it appereth nat that they do ſo, but that they rather continue ſtyll after the olde courſe, pretendynge by confederacies and worldely policies, and ſtreyte cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to rule the people, and that is greately to be lamented, and it wyll be harde for them to brynge it ſo about.</p>
               <p>But yf they wolde a lyttle meken them ſelfe, and withdrawe ſuche thynges as haue brought the people into this mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure and grudge: they ſhulde anone brynge a newe lyghte of grace into the worlde, and brynge the people to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte loue and obedience to theyr ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. And here me thynketh I myght ſaye ferther in one thynge / and that is this / that as longe as ſpirituall rulers wyll either pretende, that theyr aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is ſo hygh / and ſo immediatly deri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued of god, that the people are bounde to obeye them / and to accepte all that
<pb facs="tcp:4938:7"/>
they do and teache / withoute argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes reſiſtence or grudgyng ayenſt them, or that they wyll pretende, that no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulte is in them, but in the people, and wyll yet contynue ſtyll in the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and after the ſame worldly counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, as they do now, and haue don late tyme paſt: The lyght of grace that is ſpoken of before, wyll nat appere, but that bothe partyes ſhall walke in this darknes of malice and diuiſion, as they haue done in tyme paſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other occaſyon of this diuiſion. The ſeconde Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here haue ben made in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt many good law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es by the chirch for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good ordre of ſpyrytuall men / which were right neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to be kepte to this day: whiche now be altered eyther by a lawe made to the contrarye, or by ſomme euylle cuſtome brought vp and ſuffered agaynſte them. And I ſhal brefly recite ſome of them, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4938:7"/>
I haue founde them wrytten by other before this tyme.</p>
               <p>¶Fyrſte there was a lawe made / that a man well approued in his werkes and doctrine ſhulde be made a byſſhop, and nat a chylde ne a carnall man / or that is vnlerned in ſpyrytuall thynges.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that nothynge ſhulde be gyuen in any place for buryals / confeſſion, gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of ordres / ne for any of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, nor for any promocion.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that byſſhoppes &amp; preſtes ſhuld nat be at vayn worldly ſightes or pleys, ne delyte in them.</p>
               <p>¶That it is nat laufull for a byſſhoppe or preeſte to be abſente on the ſondaye, but to be at maſſes, and that faſtynge.</p>
               <p>¶That no preeſt ſhulde eat fleſſhe from Quinquageſime to Eſter.</p>
               <p>¶That preſtes ſhulde faſt Aduent.</p>
               <p>¶That byſſhoppes and preeſtes, and eſpecyally monkes and religyous / ſhall ſtudye in heuenly ſcriptures / all lernyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and practyſes of litygyous thynges lefte and ſet aparte.</p>
               <p>¶That the byſſhop ſhall euery yere go aboute his dioces with great diligence,
<pb facs="tcp:4938:8"/>
and effecte.</p>
               <p>¶That heuenly ſcriptures be redde at the byſſhops table.</p>
               <p>¶That a clerke full of fowle wordes ſhall be put from his office.</p>
               <p>¶That the wages of clerkes ſhalbe gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen after theyr merites.</p>
               <p>¶That preeſtes ſhal eſchewe feaſtes at mariages.</p>
               <p>¶That clerkes ſhall comme in no ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes.</p>
               <p>¶That a byſſhope ſhall haue poore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, lodgyng, and table, and fedynge for poore men.</p>
               <p>¶That a byſſhop ſhal not lyghtly ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue for tranſytorie thynges.</p>
               <p>¶That clerkes ſhulde rather ſtudie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr bretherne that varie be brought to peace, than to iudgement.</p>
               <p>¶That a clerke ſhulde inſtructe euery man with his wordes, and to the entent that poore men ſhuld not be greued, that they ſhulde get theyr lyuyng with ſome handy crafte, as ſaynt Paule dyd.</p>
               <p>¶That clerkes ſhall nat take vppon them the actes or procuracyons of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4938:8"/>¶That laye men ſhal not make clerkes theyr factoures or gouernoures vnder them.</p>
               <p>¶That monkes after the counſeylle of Calcidonence, ſhalbe holly entendynge to faſtynges and prayers in the places where they renounced the worlde, and that they forſake not theyr monaſteries for no buſynes of the churche ne of the worlde.</p>
               <p>¶That clerkꝭ that cuſtomably be play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at tables or hunters, ſhalbe prohybit of houſlynge. And ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom vpon Mathewe the .xxi. Chapiter ſayth, that as of the temple comethe out all goodnes / ſo of the temple al euyl pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedeth. And therfore it foloweth, that if preeſthode be hole, all the churche flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſheth: And if it be corrupte, the fayth and vertue of the people fadeth alſo and falleth awaye: as if thou ſee a tree that hath wethered leues, thou knoweſt ther by that there is a defaut in the rote / ſoo whan thou ſeeſt the people lyue out of good ordre, knowe it for certayne, that theyr preeſthode is not hole ne ſounde.</p>
               <p>And therfore if it were aſked / where is
<pb facs="tcp:4938:9"/>
now the deuocion and obedience of the inferiours, the defence of knyghtes, the peace of Chriſten prynces / to the ende that they, beynge at a concorde, myght reſyſt and feight againſt ſiſmatikes and infidels, recouerynge agayne regions, whiche they haue nowe taken fro chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men, &amp; peruerted them: It myght be anſwered / that they be gone throughe brekynge of ſuche lawes.</p>
               <p>¶Many of theſe ſayenges and dyuces other here omytted, be the ſayenges of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>Gerson</abbr> cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celler of Paris, in a tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that is called in latyne, Declaratio defectuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> virorum eccleſiaſticorum. In whiche treatyſe he recyteth alſo dyuers abuſyons / whereof I ſhall recyte parte vnder the maner of queſtyons for ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as he doth, as well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng other countreys as this / that they may the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be knowen and auoyded.</p>
               <p>¶Fyrſt he aſketh this queſtion. What it auayleth / or what profiteth the church the ſuperfluous pompe of prelates and cardynalles, and what meaneth it?</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that one man hathe .iiii. v. vi. or viii. benefices, whereof he is nat percaſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4938:9"/>
worthy to haue one, wherwith .viii. per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons might be ſuſteined, that giue them ſelf to lernyng / prayer, &amp; to the ſeruice of god? Here (ſaythe he) take hede. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hors, dogges, byrdes, and the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous company of men of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhulde rather eate the patrimonie of the churche, than the poore menne of Chriſt / or that it be expended in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of god, and to the conuerſion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, or in ſuche other werkes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye and pietie? O howe many places (ſaythe he) ordeyned for the ſeruice of god in Rome or elles where / be nowe through the negligence of the prelates deſolate and diſtroyed? O howe is hit that the ſwerde of holye churche / that is the ſentence of Excommunication, to her owne diſpite and reproofe, is ſo lyghtly drawen out: and for ſo lyttell a thynge (as ſometyme for dette) is ſo cruelly executed vpon poore men? What is it alſo, that one cauſe vppon a ſmalle thynge ſhall contynue ſo many yeres? and why is not that lengthe of tyme / whiche is the ſpoyler and robber of poore men, in ſomme conuenient maner
<pb facs="tcp:4938:10"/>
cutte away? why is it not rather mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully appoynted to the Iewes conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, ſomme reaſonable lyuynge of theyr owne goodes rather than by extreme ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſite to compelle them to forſake the fayth agayne / and to reproue chriſten men / that they be cruelle and haue no pitie? Iudge ye alſo (ſayth he) whether ſo great varietie of ymages &amp; pictures be expedient: and whether they do not peruert ſom ſymple ꝑſons to ydolatrie? But here it is to be nooted / that Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gerſon fyndeth not defaulte in ſettynge vp of ymages / for he commendeth it in many places of his werkes, but he fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth defaulte at the varietie of them in theyr peyntyng and garnyſſhyng with golde / ſyluer, precious ſtones, and ſuche other / with ſo great ryches about them / that ſome ſymple perſons myght lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be enduced to beleue ſom ſpecial wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng to be in the ymages / that is not in them in dede. And ſo he fyndeth defaute at the abuſe of ymages: and not at the ſettyng vppe of ymages. Diſcuſſe alſo (ſayth the ſayde Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gerſon) whether ſo large exempcions as ſome haue / be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4938:10"/>
expedient? and whether it be profitable ſo to lede them fro theyr ordinaryes? Serche alſo ſaythe he, if there be not ſome apocrifate wrytynges, or prayers / or hymnes by proceſſe of tyme / (ſome of purpoſe, ſom by negligence) brought vp to the hurte of the fayth? but than he aſketh: whether al prelates and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes be gyltie in the articles aboue reher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, and he ſaythe our lorde forbede it. For lyke as Helyas, whan he had went that all the people of Iſraell hadde bene fallen to ydolatrie / herde our lorde ſaye, I haue yet reſerued ſeuen thouſand me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that neuer bowed theyr knees before Baale: ryght ſo it maye be ſayde, that nowe in theſe dayes our lorde hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ryghte many good menne bothe ſpirituall and temporalle / that be not gyltie in any of the ſayde articles, ne yet partie in any maner to the ſayde diuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, whiche through helpe of grace, and with the fauour of the ſuperiours / ſhall be ryghte well able to brynge the other to good accorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:4938:11"/>
               <head>¶An other occaſyon of this dyuyſyon. The thyrde Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be many lawes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees made by the churche wherin it is recited, ꝙ laici ſunt clericis infeſti, that is to ſaye, that laye men be cruell to clerkes / and therfore the churche hath therupon made dyuers lawes to opreſſe that crueltie / as in them appereth. And therupon hath folowed, that whan pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes haue red the lawes / they haue iuged therby, that theyr reulers haue knowen ſome great crueltie in laye men agaynſt clerkes. For elles they wolde not haue put tho wordes in to theyr lawes, and that hath cauſed many ſpyrytuall men to adiuge the more lyghtly, that ſuche thynges as laye men haue done concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge them, hath rather ben done of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lice and cruelte than otherwiſe, and that iudgement in proceſſe of tyme hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to confedre them ſelfe togider, to reſiſte that malice / whiche they many tymes by occaſion of the ſayde wordes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4938:11"/>
haue iudged to be greatter than it was, and haue many tymes recited the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / affermynge them to be true: and therfore they haue extended all lawes / that be made agaynſt laye men the more extremely agaynſte them: Whereby the people in many countreys haue ben ſo ofte greued and oppreſſed that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue grutched marueyllouſly at it. And whan laye men haue redde tho wordes, they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therby, that the makers of tho lawes / whiche repreſent in them the eſtate of al ſpyrytuall men, haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that the makers therof thoughte, that lay men were cruelle agaynſt them and where cruelte is iudged to be / there is no loue. For like as nothyng helpeth more to noryſſhe loue in a man / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he maye knowe, that the other louethe hym, though he neuer receyued any pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte by hym: ſo nothynge nouryſſheth more dyuyſion and diſcorde, than that a man know that another loueth him not / though percaſe he knowe / that he neuer dyd hym hurte / ne entendeth not to do. And therfore whan lay men haue by tho wordes taken occaſyon to thynke / that
<pb facs="tcp:4938:12"/>
ſpyrytuall men haue adiuged crueltie in them: they haue anon iudged that ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual men loue them not and that hath in theyr hartes broken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charitable loue and obedyence / that they ought to haue to ſpyrytuall reulers: and thoughe the occaſion of this article be not vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly (for al lay men haue not ſene tho wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) yet the reporte of tho wordes hath come to the knowlege of many lay men, as well by ſpyrytuall men as by tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men, that haue redde them: whiche by longe contynuance hath noryſſhed one great branche of this diuiſyon / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I ſuppoſe veryly wylle neuer fullye be appeyſed, tyll the ſpyrytuall gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours wil be as dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to make lawes, that ſhal brynge in mekenes among ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall men, and that may enduce them charytablye to ſuffre ſome tyme them that offende them, as they haue bene in tyme paſt to make lawes to ſet ſpyrytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all men in ſuche caſe, that they may cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte all them and kepe them vnder, that wyll any thynge reſyſte them. And lyke as many ſpirituall men haue myſordred them ſelfe agaynſte laye men, not onely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4938:12"/>
in ſuche thynges as be partely touched before, but alſo in wordes / affermynge ſomtyme, that lay men loue not preſtes: ſo in likewiſe ſome lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſordre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe in wordes agaynſt preſtes, and wil ſay, that there is no good preſte, or that all preſtes be nought: and ſome, as it is ſayde / wyll call them ſomtyme horeſon preſtes. And if all theſe wordes were prohybyte on bothe ſydes vpon greate paines / I thynke it wold do great good in this behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other cauſe of this dyuyſion The fourth Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He harde &amp; extreme lawes that are made for layenge violent handes vpon cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and ſuche other ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall perſones / hath ben an other cauſe of this diuiſion. For they be very parcyalle / as to the reders wylle appere, and they be alſo ſo generalle,
<pb facs="tcp:4938:13"/>
that nether kynge nor lorde be not excep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in them, but that they ſhulde goo to the pope to be aſſoyled. And the ſayde lawes be .xvii. q. iiii. ſi quis ſuadente diabolo et ex. de ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenc. exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municac. ca. Non dubiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et Ca. mulieris: et Ca. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit: et ca. ea noſcitur. &amp; in many other chapiters there / et ex. de ſentenc. excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municac. li. vi. ca. religioſo. And theſe lawes be ſuche / that if a manne in vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence lay his hande only vpon a clerke / that he is accourſed: but thoughe a clerke beate a laye manne wrongfully / and with violence, he is not accourſed. And this parcialyte hathe done greatte hurte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other occaſion of this dyuyſion. The fyft Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Houghe there be dyuers good and reaſonable arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ordeyned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church to be redde openlye to the people at certain dayes, by the churche therto aſſygned / which com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4938:13"/>
is called the general ſentence: yet manye curates and theyr paryſh preſtes ſometyme rede onely parte of the arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles / and omytte parte therof / eyther for ſhortnes of tyme / or els to take ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycles as ſerue moſte to theyr purpoſe. And ſomtyme, as it is ſayd / they adde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s after their mynde, that be not putte in to the ſayde general ſentence. And whan the artycles be ſo choſen out / they ſounde to ſo great par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialite and fauour for ſpiritual men, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for payeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of tythes, offerynges, mortuaries / and ſuche other duetyes to the churche, or for the mayntenaunce of that they calle the liberties of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, as that no preeſte nor clerke. &amp;c. ſhal not be put to anſwere before lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpecyallye where theyr bodyes ſhuld be arreſted, or that no impoſicions ſhulde be layde vpon the churche by temporall power, or agaynſt them that with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence lay handes vpon preeſt or clerk / or ſuche other: that the people be greatly offended therby, and thynke great par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialite in them, and iuge them rather to be made of a pryde and couetyſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:4938:14"/>
churche: than of any charite to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, wherby many doo rather dyſpyſe them than obeye them. And I ſuppoſe veryly, that this diuiſyon wyl neuer be perfitely and charitably refourmed and brought to good accorde, tyll the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come to this poynt / that they ſhall greatlye feare and drede to ronne in to the leeſte cenſure of the churche. And that wyll neuer be, tyll the heedes ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall wyll refourme them ſelfe, and ſhewe a fatherlye loue vnto the people, and not extende the ſentences of the churche vppon ſo lyghte cauſes, and vppon ſuche parcialytie, as they haue doone in tyme paſte. And if they wyll refourme theſe poyntes before reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſomme other hereafter folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge, I ſuppoſe verylye the people wylle gladdely here them and folowe, them. For than, as the goſpelle ſaythe they be theyr verye ſhepardes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yf it were ordeyned as well by auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torytie of parlyamente as of conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / that ſuche artycles ſhulde be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſed and putte in to the generalle ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that ſhulde ſtyrre as well ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualle
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4938:14"/>
menne, as temporalle menne to loue vertue / and flee vyces / to loue trouth and plainnes, and to flee falſhod and doublenes / and that none vpon a payne ſhulde adde or dyminyſſhe any thynge concernynge the ſayde articles: I thynke it wolde helpe moche to make a good agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this diuiſion, and to contynue the ſame, with loue and drede betwexte the reulers ſpirituall and the people, as there oughte to be. And yf lyke artycles were deuiſed to refrayne ſpyrytuall men fro gyuynge hereafter any ferther occaſion to this diuiſion, or any other lyke: and they to be redde at viſitations / Seenes, &amp; ſuche other lyke places / wher preſtes aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of theyr ordinaries / with certayne paynes to be appoynted by parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; conuocacion: I thynke it wolde bryng many thynges in to good order / and helpe moche to a good reformation of this diuiſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other occaſion of this diuiſion. The ſyxt Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4938:15"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N other occaſion of this di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſion hathe partely ryſen by temporal men, that haue deſyred moche to haue the famyliaritie of preeſtes in theyr games and diſportes, and haue vſed to make moche more of them that were compenable, thanne of them that were not ſo, and haue called them good felowes and good companyons. And many alſo wolde haue chapleyns, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they wolde not onlye ſuffre / but alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde to go on huntyng, haukyng / and ſuche other vayne diſportes. And ſome wolde lette them lye among other laye ſeruauntes, where they coulde ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſe prayer nor contemplation.</p>
               <p>¶And ſome of them wolde ſuffre them to go in lyueries not conuenyent in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for a preſte to were, and wolde alſo many tymes ſet them to worldely offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as to be bayliffes, receiuours / or ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes: and than whan they haue by ſuche occaſyon bene moche beten / and greatly exercyſed in ſuche worldely bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynes / ſo that the inwarde deuocyon of the harte hath ben in them as colde and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4938:15"/>
as weke in maner, as in laye men, yet yf any benefyce haue fallen voyde of theyr gyft, they wolde preferre them to it / ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as in recompens of theyr buſynes and labours, or for that they were good companyons: rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another good deuoute man / that percaſe is lerned and kepeth hym ſelfe fro ſuche worldely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyties and ydle company, or that is dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſomtyme to admonyſſhe charyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuche as he is in company with, of ſuche defautes as he ſeeth or hereth of them / and that few men do loue to here: And therfore wyll they preferre them / that wyl let them alone. And yet whan they haue ſo done, they wyl anone ſpeke euyl of preſtes / and reporte great lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in them, and lyghtly noote one preſt with an nother preſtes defaute, and that whan they haue ben partly occaſioners to theyr offences them ſelfe, as it is ſayd before. And this demenour hath thrugh a longe contynuaunce noryſſhed ſome parte of this dyuyſion, and ſo wyll it do as long as it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth. And alſo where by the lawe / preeſtes ought to be at the churche on ſondayes &amp; holy dayes, and
<pb facs="tcp:4938:16"/>
help forth the ſeruice of god in the quere and oughte alſo whan they be there to be ordered by the curate: yet neuer the leſſe many men that haue chapleynes, wyll not ſuffre them to come in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe churche, and whan they be there, they wyll not haue them ordered by the curate, but after them ſelfe: ne ſee them be in the quere, but ſendeth them many tymes on other errandes, and that in worldly matters, as cuſtomably as they do other ſeruauntes, and many ſuche chapleynes ſhewe them ſelfe euydently by theyr diligence in that behalfe / to be better contente to do that buſynes, than to be in the quere / and that maketh the curates and the neyghbours bothe to thynke a great lyghtnes in them, and do diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende them for it, and whan they here of it, they be alſo diſcontented, and theyr mayſters bothe, and ſaye the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue no thynge to do with it, and commenly other chapleynes wyll take parte in ſuche matters: wherupon dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers grudges and variances haue riſen in many places / that haue done greatte hurte in this behalf. And as it is in this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4938:16"/>
caſe of chapleynes, and ſeruyng preſtes, ſo it is alſo of chantry preſtes &amp; brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode preſtes in many places. And as it ſemethe theſe articles myght be holpen thus, that is to ſay / that it be prohibyted vpon a payne, that no preeſte ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after cuſtomablye vſe huntynge / haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge, cardes / dyce / nor ſuche other games vnſyttynge for a preeſte though percaſe he maye as for a recreacion vſe ſome honeſt diſportes for a tyme: ne cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably vſe the ale houſe or tauerne. And if any preſte vſe any ſuch vnlawful games or other demenour, not conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a preeſt, ſo moche that the people be offended by it, and fynde defaut at it, that than yf he be warned therof by an abbot and a Iuſtyce of the peace of the ſhire / where he is dwellynge, and yet he do not reforme hymſelfe: that than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde the ſayde payne, he be by conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuſpended fro miniſtryng the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, and be diſabled to take any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce, tyll he be enhabled agayne by the kynge and the ordinarie. And that it be ferther enacted / that no man ſhall haue a chapleyne hereafter / but he haue a ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge
<pb facs="tcp:4938:17"/>
houſe / and that onely in his ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng houſe, and none to haue a rydyng chapleyne vnder the degree of a baron / and that he that hath a ſtondyng houſe, and hathe alſo a chapleyne, ſhall vppon a payn prouide for his chapleyn a ſecret lodgyng with locke &amp; key / that he maye lodge fro the commen recourſe of the laye ſeruantes, and vſe hym ſelfe therin conueniently in redynge / prayer, or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>templatyon / or ſuche other labours and buſynes as be conuenyent for a preeſte to vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other cauſe of the ſayd dyuyſion. The ſeuenth Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N other occaſion of the ſaid dyuyſion hath bene / by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of dyuers ſutes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ben taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of offyce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called in latyn, ex offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ꝑties haue not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who hath accuſed them, &amp; therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue ſomtyme ben cauſed to abiure in cauſes of hereſies: ſomtyme to do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4938:17"/>
to pay great ſommes of money for rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge therof, whiche vexacion &amp; char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the parties haue thought haue come to them by the iudges and the offycers of the ſpyrytuall courte / for they haue knowen none other accuſers / and that hath cauſed moche people in diuers par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes of this realme to thynke great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and parcialytie in the ſpiritual iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And yf a man be ex officio brought before the ordynarye for hereſy / yf he be notably ſuſpected of hereſye: he muſte pourge hym ſelfe after the wyl of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary / or be accurſed, and that is by the lawe, extra de hereticis. Ca. Ad abolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. And that is thoughte by many to be a very harde lawe, for a man may be ſuſpected and nat gyltie, and ſo be dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to a purgacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without profe or with out offence in hym, or be accurſed: and it appereth de hereticis .li. vi. in the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter In fidei fauorem, that they that be accurſed, and alſo partyes to the ſame offens may be wytnes in hereſie: and in the chapiter accuſatus, pag. licet, it appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth, that yf a man be ſworne to ſaye the trouthe concernynge hereſie, as well of
<pb facs="tcp:4938:18"/>
hym ſelfe as of other / and he fyrſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth nothynge, and after contrarye to his fyrſt ſayenge he appeleth bothe hym ſelfe and other: yf it appere by many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt tokens, that he doeth it nat of lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mynde, ne of hatred / nor for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of moneye: that than his wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in fauoure of the faythe ſhall ſtonde as well agaynſte hym ſelfe, as agaynſte other: and yet hit appereth euidentlye in the ſame courte, and in the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he is a periured perſone.</p>
               <p>This is a daungerous lawe, and more lyke to cauſe vntrewe and vnlawfulle men to condempne innocentes, than to condempne offenders. And it helpeth lyttell, that if there be tokens / that it is nat done of hatred / nor for corruption of money: that it ſhulde be taken: for ſome tyme a wolfe may ſhew hym ſelfe in the apparelle of a lambe. And yf the iudge be parcyall, ſuche tokens may be ſoner accepted than truely ſhewed. And in the chapiter there, that begynneth Statuta quedam / it is decreed, that yf the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe or other enquerours of hereſy, ſe that any greate daunger myghte come
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4938:18"/>
to the accuſours or wytnes of hereſie by the great power of them that be accuſed: that than they maye commaunde, that the names of the accuſoures or wytneſſe ſhall nat be ſhewed but to the byſſhop or enquerours / or ſuche other lerned men as be called to them, and that ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, thoughe they be nat ſhewed to the partie. And for the more indempnitie of the ſayde accuſoures and wytneſſe it is there decreed, that the byſſhoppe or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queroures maye enioyne ſuche as they haue ſhewed the names of ſuche wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto, to kepe them cloſe vpon payn of excommunication, for diſcloſyng that ſecrete without theyr lycens. And ſurely this is a ſore lawe / that a manne ſhall be condempned, and nat knowe the names of them that be cauſers therof.</p>
               <p>¶And though the ſayd lawe ſeme to be made vpon a good conſideracion for the indempnitie of the accuſours and wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet it ſemeth that that conſydera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon can nat ſuffyce to proue the lawe reaſonable. For it ſemeth that the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoures and wytnes myghte be ſaued fro daunger by another way / and that is by
<pb facs="tcp:4938:19"/>
this way. If the byſſhop or inquerours drede that the accuſoures and wytnes might take hurt, as is ſayd before: than myght they ſhewe it to the kynge and to his counſaylle / beſechynge his grace of helpe in that behalfe, to ſaue and defende the accuſoures and witnes fro the extort power of them that be accuſed: And yf they wold do ſo: it is nat to ſuppoſe, but that the kynge wold ſufficiently prouide for theyr ſaufegarde: But for as moche as it ſhulde ſeme, that ſpyrytuall men ſomwhat pretende to punyſſhe hereſyes only of theyr owne power, without cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for any aſſiſtance of the temporal po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer / therfore they make ſuche lawes / as may helpe forthe theyr purpoſe, as they thynke: but ſurely that is nat the charita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble way, to put the knowlege of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the accuſors and witnes fro hym that is accuſed, for yf he knew them, he might percaſe allege and proue ſo great and ſo vehemente cauſe of rancoure and malice in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that accuſe hym, that theyr ſayenges by no lawe ought nat to ſtand agaynſt hym. And that ſpyrytuall men pretende, that they onely ſhuld haue the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4938:19"/>
hole inquerie and puniſſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of hereſy, it apereth extra de hereticis .li. vi. ca. vt inquiſitionis, ꝑag. prohibemꝰ: where all powers / and al lordes temporall and reulers be prohibite / that they ſhall nat in any maner take knowlege or Iudge vpon hereſie, ſithe it is mere ſpirituall, and he that inquereth of hereſie, taketh knowlege of hereſie. And ſo the ſumme called ſumma roſella, taketh it titulo ex communicac. perag. iiii. And yf that be true, it ſemeth than that all iuſtyces of peace in this realm be excomunicate: for they by auctoritie of the kinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and alſo by ſtatute inquere of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. And I thynk it is nat in the church to prohibite that: for though it were ſo, that the temporall men maye nat iudge / what is hereſie and what nat, yet they may, as it ſemeth, by theyr owne aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie inquere of it / and enforme the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, what they haue founde. And alſo yf a metropolytane with all his clergye and people of his dioces fel into heriſie: it wolde be harde to redreſſe it withoute temporal power. And therfore temporal men be redye and are bounde to be redy
<pb facs="tcp:4938:20"/>
to oppreſſe hereſies / whan they ryſe: as ſpirituall men be. And therfore ſpiritual men may nat take all the thanke to them ſelfe / whan hereſyes be punyſſhed, as thoughe theyr charitie and power onely dyd it, for they haue the fauor and helpe of temporall men to do it, or elles many tymes it wolde nat be brought about.</p>
               <p>Neuertheles my entente is nat to proue the ſaid lawes all holly to be cruell &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſonable, for I know well, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is right expedient, that ſtrayt lawes be made for puniſſhment of hereſies, that be hereſies in dede, more rather than any other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and that the diſcretion of the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſpyrytuall may ryght well aſwage the rygour of the ſayde lawes, and vſe them more fauorably agaynſt them that be innocent, than agaynſte them that be wylfull offendours, yf they wyll chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſerche for the truthe. But ſurely yf the ſayde lawes ſhulde be put in to the handelynge of cruell iudges, it myghte happen that they ſhulde many tymes pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſſh innocentes as wel as offendours / but I truſt in god, it is nat ſo. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les whether it be ſoo or nat / certayne it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4938:20"/>
is that there is a great rumour amonge the peple, that it is ſo / &amp; that ſpiritual me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> punyſſhe nat hereſye onely for zele of the fayth, and of a loue &amp; a zele to the people, with a fatherly pietie to them that ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende / as they oughte to do / how greate offenders ſo euer they be, but that they do it rather to oppreſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſpeketh any thynge agaynſte the worldly power or ryches of ſpyrytuall men, or agaynſte the greate confederacie, that (as many men ſay) is in them to maynteygne it. And though many ſpyrytuall men may be founde, that haue ryght many greate vertues and great gyftes of god, as cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytye, lyberalytie, pacyence, ſobrenes, temperaunce, cunnyng, and ſuche other / yet it wyll be harde to fynde any one ſpyrytuall man, that is nat enfecte with the ſayd deſyre and affection to haue the worldely honoure of preſtes exalted and preferred / &amp; therfore if any lay ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> report any euyll of a preeſt / though it be openly knowen / that it is as he ſayeth, yet they wyll be more diligente to cauſe the laye man to ceſſe of that ſayenge, than to do that in theym is, to refourme that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4938:21"/>
in the preeſt / that is ſpoken of, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge as hit were an occaſion to doo the leſſe in ſuche reformacions, bycauſe laye men ſpeke ſo moche agaynſt them: But ſurely that wyll be none excuſe to ſpyrytuall rulers afore god / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal aſke accompte of his people / that were commytted vnto theyr kepynge.</p>
               <p>¶And if this diuiſion be ſuffred to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue, it is nat vnlyke, but that greate bendynge ſhall folow on bothe parties, whereby great hurte and inconuenience may growe vnto moche people. And I ſee none that may ſet a meane waye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene theſe extremities, ne that mindeth any thynge to do good in it, but the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges grace and his parliamente. And I thynke verelye that they are bounde in conſcyence to folowe it with effecte, tyll the diuiſion be clerely ceſſed. Our lorde of his mercy ſende them grace to do it. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other occaſyon of this dyuyſyon. The eyght Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4938:21"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a commen opinyon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong doctours, that none is an heretike for that onely that he erreth / but for that he defendeth opynatyfelye his errour. And therefore he that erreth of ſimplicite, may in no wyſe be ſayd an heretyke. And ſumma roſella, in the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hereticus in principio, ſayeth: that a man may erre, and meryte therby: and he putteth this example. If a ſymple vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lerned man here the preachynge of his byſſhop / that preacheth happly agaynſt the faithe / and he beleueth it with a redy mynde to obey: this man meriteth, and yet he erreth: but that is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonde where ignorance excuſeth. Than it ſemeth, that it is nat ynough to proue that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an heretike / for that he hath holden opinions ayenſte that the church teacheth / ne that he oughte nat to make any purgation nor abiuration for it: for that that he hielde in ſuche caſe was nat his faythe / but the faythe of the churche was his faythe, though happly he were nat than fully auyſed of it. And therfore ſaynt Aidan, whan he helde the wronge
<pb facs="tcp:4938:22"/>
parte of kepynge of Eeſter was no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retyke / and ſome ſaye that ſaynt Chadde was of the ſame opynyon as ſaynte Ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan was, whiche in lykewyſe was no heretike, for theyr deſyre was to knowe the truthe: and therefore it is nat redde that they made eyther purgacyon or abiuracion, ne yet the abbot Ioachym, whiche neuertheles erred / for he was redy to ſubmytte hym to the determyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the chyrche / and therfore he was neyther holden as an heretyke / ne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to abiure. Than yf this be ſothe, it were greate pitie / yf it ſhulde be true, as is reported, that there ſhulde be ſo great a deſyre in ſome ſpyrytuall men to haue men abiured, or haue the extreme punyſſhement for hereſie / as it is ſayde there is. For as ſome haue reported, yf any woll wytnes, that a man hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any thynge, that is hereſie, though he ſpeke it onely of an ignoraunce, or of a paſſyon, or if he canne by interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes and queſtions be dryuen to confeſſe any thynge / that is prohybyted by the churche: anone they wyll dryue hym to abiure, or holde hym atteynted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4938:22"/>
examining the intent or cauſe of his ſayenge, or whether he had a mynde to be refourmed or nat: and that is a verye ſoore way, our lorde be more mercyfull to our ſoules, than ſo greuouſly to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe vs for euery lyght defaut.</p>
               <p>And here ſome ſaye that bycauſe there is ſo greate a deſyre in ſpyrytuall men, to haue menne abiure / and to be noted with hereſye / and that ſome, as it were of a polycye, do noyſe it, that the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aulme is full of heretyckes, more than it is in dede: that it is very peryllous, that ſpyrytuall men ſhulde haue aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie to arreſt a man for euery lyght ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pection, or complaynte of hereſye, tyll that deſyre of punyſſhement in ſpyrytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all men be ceaſſed and goone: but that they ſhulde make proceſſe agaynſt them to brynge theym in vppon payne of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge: and thanne, yf they tary fourty dayes, the kynges lawes to brynge them in by a wrytte De excommunicato ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendo, and ſo to be broughte fourthe oute of the kynges Gaole to aunſwere. But ſurely, as it is ſomewhat touched
<pb facs="tcp:4938:23"/>
before in the .vii. chap. it ſemeth that the church in tyme paſt hath don what they coulde to brynge about, that they might punyſſhe hereſie of them ſelfe / without callynge for any helpe therin of the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler power.</p>
               <p>¶And therefore they haue made lawes that heretykes myghte be arreſted and put in pryſon / and ſtockes yf nede were / as appereth Clementinis de hereticis. Ca. multorum querela. And after at the ſpeciall callyng on of the ſpiritualtie / it was enacted by parlyament, that ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries myght arreſt men for hereſie: for ſumme men thynke, that the ſayde Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentyne was nat of effect in the kynges lawe to arreſt any man for hereſie: But if a man were openly and notably ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of hereſie / and that there were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient recorde and wytnes agaynſt hym / &amp; there were alſo a doubte that he wolde flee and nat appere, wherby he myghte enfecte other: it ſemeth conuenient that he be areſted by the body: but nat vpon euery lyght complaynt, that full lightly may be vntrewe. And it wyll be ryghte expedient, that the kynges highnes and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4938:23"/>
his counſaylle loke ſpecyally vpon this matter, and nat to ceaſſe / tylle hit be brought to more quietnes than it is yet, and to ſe with great dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that pride, couetiſe, nor worldly loue be no iudges, nor innocentes be punyſſhed, ne yet that wylfull offenders go nat without dewe correction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other cauſe of this diuiſion. ¶The .ix. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N other occaſion of this diuiſion hath riſen by the extremities that haue ben ſhewed in ſutes taken in the ſpyrytuall courtes, by ſpyrytuall men, for there hath therby riſen an opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che people / that a man were as good or better to let a ſpyrytuall man haue at the begynnyng all that he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, as to ſtryue with hym in the ſpyrytuall lawe for it. In ſo moche / that as it is ſayde ſuche extremities haue bene vſed in the
<pb facs="tcp:4938:24"/>
ſpirituall lawe for tythes, that no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription / cuſtome, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſition, nor other plee ſhall be admytted in the ſpyrytuall lawe agaynſt them. And ſurely yf that be trewe, it is a great parcyalyte, and a great denyeng of Iuſtyce. And therfore it wolde be refourmed. And as for mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries they be adnulled all redy by ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute: But yet begynnethe to ryſe oone thynge to maynteyne the fyrſt dyuyſion concernynge ſuche mortuaryes, yf it be ſuffered to contynue, and that is / that many curates / nat regardynge the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſtatute in that behalfe, perſwade theyr paryſſhens, whan they be ſycke, to beleue that they can nat be ſaued, but they reſtore them as moche as the olde mortuarie wolde haue amounted to.</p>
               <p>And ſurelye, the Curates that by that meanes get any recompence, by gyfte, or by queſt, are bounde in conſcience to reſtytucyon. For he is deceyued in his gyfte or bequeſt. For it procedeth nat of a free libertie / but vppon that vntrue infourmacyon. And lyke as a contracte, wherby a man is deceiued in that thyng that is ſolde, holdeth nat in conſcience,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4938:24"/>
as yf a manne ſelle copper for golde, or wyne myxte with water for pure wyne: and ſo it is whan a man maketh a gyfte or a bequeſte vpon an vntrue ſurmyſe. And that no man is bounden in conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to reſtore for his mortuarye nowe, ſythe the ſtatute of Mortuaryes was made / it maye appere thus. It is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by them, that be lerned in the lawe of this realme, that the parlyamente hathe an abſolute power, as to the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyon of all temporall thynges within thys realme, in whoſe handes ſo euer they be / ſpyrytualle, or temporalle / to take theym from one manne, and gyue theym to an other / wythoute any cauſe or conſyderacyon. For yf they doo it, it byndeth in the lawe. And yf there be a conſideracion / that hit byndethe in lawe and conſcience. And certayne it is, that all ſuche Mortuaryes were tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralle goodes / thoughe they were claymed by ſpyrytualle menne: And the cauſe why they were taken awaye was, for as moche as there were fewe thynges within this realme, that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more varyaunce among the people,
<pb facs="tcp:4938:25"/>
than they dyd / whan they were ſuffered: for they were taken ſo farre agaynſt the order of the kynges lawes, and againſt Iuſtyce and ryght as ſhall hereafter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere. Fyrſte they were taken nat onely after the dethe of the huſbande, but alſo after the dethe of the wyfe, whiche after the lawes of the realme had no goodes, but that it was taken of the huſbandes goodes / and they were taken alſo of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes and chyldren as well infantes as other. And if a man died by the waye, and had an houſholde in an other place, he ſhulde paye mortuaries in bothe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And ſome tyme whan the parſon / and vicar of a church appropried / vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the mortuaries, the people (as it hath ben reported) haue ben enforced, er they coulde ſytte in reſte / to pay in ſome places mortuaries to them bothe. And ſomtyme the curates wolde prohybyte pore men to ſell theyr goodes in tyme of theyr ſicknes, if they were ſuche goodes as were lyke to be theyr mortuaries: for they wolde ſay it was done in defraude of the churche. And yf the quyck goodes were better than the deed goodes, they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4938:25"/>
wolde in ſome places take the quycke: And yf the deade goodes were better than the quycke, they wolde take the dead. And the mortuaryes muſte be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered furthewith, or elles the bodye ſhulde nat be buryed. And they preſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to haue ryghte to mortuaries onely by the preſcription of the ſpirituall law. And vnder that maner mortuaries en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſſed dayly in manye places / where they hadde nat bene vſed before / and of lykelyhode wolde haue gone farther, yf they had nat ben ſtopped in tyme. And they were in many places taken in ſuche maner / that it made the people to thynk, that the curates loued theyr mortuaries better than theyr lyues. And thereupon roſe in many places great diuiſion and grudge betwyxte theym, whiche broke the peace, loue, &amp; charitie that ſhuld be betwene the curate and his paryſſhens, to the greate vnquietnes of many of the kynges ſubiectes, as well ſpirituall as temporall / and to the great daunger and perylle of theyr ſoules. For theſe cauſes the ſaid mortuaries be adnulled by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament / as well in conſcience as in the
<pb facs="tcp:4938:26"/>
lawe: And yet it is ſayde that ſome cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates vſe great extremities concernyng the ſayde mortuaries a nother waye: and that is this. If the executours at the fyrſte requeſt pay nat the money that is appoynted by the ſtatute / they wyl anon haue a citacion agaynſt hym, And there he ſhalbe ſo handeled, that as it is ſayde, it hadde ben mooſte commenly moche better too hym too haue payde his olde mortuarie, than the coſtes and expenſes that he ſhall paye there. And yf it be ſo, it wolde be refourmed. And ſurely this matter wolde be groundly loked vpon: for ſome men ſaye, that the ſute in that caſe oughte to be taken in the kynges courte / and nat in the ſpyrytuall courte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Other occaſions of this diuiſion. The tenthe Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He extreme and couetouſe demeanour of ſome curates with theyr pariſſhens / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of mencion is partely made hereafter, hathe ben an other
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4938:26"/>
cauſe of this diuiſion: And though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpyrytuall men be nat felowes with them in the extremities: yet non of them that haue ben beſt and mooſt indifferent haue nat done any thynge to refourme theym that vſe ſuche extremities / ne to make them thynke, that any defaut is in theym in that doynge: but rather, as it were with a deafe eare, haue diſſimuled it, and ſuffred it paſſe ouer / and haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured them ſelfe more to oppreſſe all the lay people, that wolde ſpeke againſt it, than to refourme them that do it.</p>
               <p>And ſome of the ſayde extremytyes be thoſe. Some ſay, that in takynge of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, curates in ſome places wyll haue the .x. parte of euery thynge within the paryſſhe, that is tythable, though theyr predeceſſours withoute tyme of mynde, haue bene contented withoute hit: and though there be ſufficient beſyde for the curate to lyue on, or though he hath nat knowen, but that percaſe ſome other thynge in olde tyme hath bene aſſigned in recompens for it. And in ſom place is aſked, as it is ſayde, tythe bothe of che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyns and egges, and in ſome place of
<pb facs="tcp:4938:27"/>
mylke and cheſe, and in ſome place the x. parte of the grounde, and alſo of that that falleth on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And in ſome places is claimed tithe of ſeruantes wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges without deduction: And it is but in few places that any ſeruaunte ſhall goo quite without ſom tithe payeng / though he haue ſpent al in ſyckenes, or vpon his father and mother / or ſuche other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie expences.</p>
               <p>And in ſom places if a pariſſhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue nat x. calues that yere, the curate wyll put the tythynge of tyll another yere / and than to take a tythe calfe, accomptynge bothe yeres togyther / rather than he wold the fyrſt yere take the money, that is in that caſe aſſigned by the lawe. And they doo lykewyſe of lambes, pygges, and ſuche other thynges. Alſo in many places the curates take more at marya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, buryals, and obites, than they were wont to do, and wyll nat bury a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that dyeth within the paryſſhe, but he haue ſome what for it. Alſo ſome cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates / whan there is any varyaunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene hym and any of his pariſſhens, or that any of his paryſſhens be in his det,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4938:27"/>
hathe prohybyte them fro howſell tylle he be payde. And it hathe bene ſomtyme ſene, that whan a poore man hathe ben ſette to be houſeled, the curate hathe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the paryſſhe vpon ſome ſuche di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſure cauſed hym to ryſe and goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye without houſell, to his rebuke.</p>
               <p>And though theſe abuſyons be nat vſed vnyuerſallye (god forbyd they ſhulde) for there be many good curates and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpyrytuall men, that wolde nat vſe them for the wynnynge or leſynge of no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erthly thynges: yet whan people of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers contrees mete to gyther / and one of them telleth an other of ſome ſuche extre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mities in ſome curates in his contreye, and the other lykewyſe to hym: anone they eſteme ſuche couetyſe and extreme delynge to be in al curates. And though they do nat well in that doynge / for the offence of one prieſte is no offence to an other, yf they ſo wyll take it: Yet ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men do nothynge therin to brynge the people oute of that iudgement, but ſuffre ſuche abuſions to be vſed by ſome of them continually without correction / and (as I haue ſayd before) wyl rather
<pb facs="tcp:4938:28"/>
laboure to ſtoppe the mouthes of them, that wyll fynde defaulte at ſuche demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, than to helpe to refourme them that do it. And ſurely as longe as they do ſo, hit wyll be very harde to haue a good vnitie and peace in this behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Other cauſes of the ſayd diuiſion. The .xi. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N other thynge that hath cauſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to grudge agaynſte the pope &amp; other ſpirituall rulers hath ben the grauntynge of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons for money. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hathe benne noyſed, that the money ſhulde be beſtowed to ſomme charitable vſe, as vppon the buyldynge of ſayncte Peters churche in Rome, or to ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charitable vſe: it hathe appered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde euidently, that it hath nat ben diſpoſed to that vſe. And that hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many to thynke that the ſayde par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons were graunted rather of couetice, than of charitie, or for the helthe of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4938:28"/>
ſoules of the people. And therupon ſome haue fallen in maner in to dyſpyſynge of pardons, as though pardons graunted vpon ſuche couetiſe, ſhulde nat auaile. And becauſe the people be greately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in that iudgemente / for as to the taker, the pardone is good, though the grauntor offend in his grauntyng of the pardon. Therefore it is right neceſſary / that the rulers take hede, that pardons be herafter graunted in ſuche charitable maner, that the people ſhall haue no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ne coloure to thynke, that they be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of couetice: And than the grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toures ſhall profytte them ſelfe in theyr graunte / and the people alſo in theyr ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge, and elles it maye lyghtely hurte them bothe. And verely it were greate pitie, that any myſlykynge of pardons ſhulde growe in the hertes of the people for any miſdemeanor in the grauntours or otherwyſe / for they be ryghte neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And I ſuppoſe that if certein ꝑdons were grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted frely without money, for ſayeng of certein prayers therin to be ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed, that all miſlikynge of pardons wolde ſhortly ceſſe and vanyſſhe away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:4938:29"/>
               <head>¶An other cauſe of this dyuyſion. The .xii. Chapyter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N other cauſe of this dyuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon hathe bene by reaſon of dyuers lawes and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutyons whiche haue bene made by the churche, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme by the Pope, ſomtyme by Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / or by Metropolitanes in theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince: wherin they haue many times ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceded theyr auctoritie, and attempted in many thynges agaynſte the lawe of the realme. And yet neuertheles many prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes haue giuen full credence to them / for they haue thought that the makers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whiche were the heedes of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, wolde nat make any lawe, but by good and ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t auctoritie. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon it hathe folowed / that whan any doubte or queſtion hath ryſen vpon the ſayd lawes: all ſpiritual men in maner wolde ſtycke faſt to the lawes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temporall men by reaſon of a comen vſe and cuſtome, that they haue ſene to the contrarie, haue reſiſted them: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4938:29"/>
haue ryſen in many places great ſtryfe, varyaunces, &amp; great expences in the ſpirituall lawe. Wherby many tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall men haue thought that ſpirituall courtes be rather vſed for maintenaunce of couetiſe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for miniſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of iuſtice. And thoughe, with the mercye of oure lorde, the trouthe is nat ſo vniuerſally: yet ſome diligence wolde be taken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue that iudgement fro the people.</p>
               <p>¶And of theſe lawes is the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Bonyface the Archebyſſhoppe of Canterbury / wherby it is decreed, that he that letteth a woman couerte to make her wyll, or that letteth it to be proued, is accurſed: and the lawe of the realme is, that a woman couerte hathe no goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that ſhe may make any wyll of, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte it be of a thynge in action, or that ſhe were executrix before. And if ſhe we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſo, than with licence of her huſbande ſhe may make an executour to the intent he may leuye the dette or fulfyll the fyrſt wyll. An other lyke law is of the decree of the ryghte reuerende father in god, Roberte Wynchelſye / late archebyſſhop of Canterbury, made againſt the comen
<pb facs="tcp:4938:30"/>
cuſtom of the realme for tithe of wood: aboue .xx. yere nat to be payde / whiche cuſtome was confermed by the ſtatute made in the .xiv. yere of king E. the .iii. that is commenly called the ſtatute of Silua cedua: By reaſon of whiche de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cree great ſutes, variances, &amp; expenſes haue enſued and wyl enſue, if it be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red. wherfore the ſayde eſtatute wolde be throughly ſene: And yf hit be good, than nat to ſuffre any decree to ſtande agaynſte it / and els clerely to breke it. Other lyke lawes be the lawes that be made by the churche, that executoures ſhall nat vppon payne of curſynge, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtre, tyll they haue proued the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: where the lawe of the realme is / that they may: &amp; ſo reaſon wold that they ſhulde be: for els the goodes of the teſtatour myght be enbeſelled &amp; loſt for euer. And that lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may nat put cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to anſwer before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpecially in cri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minal cauſes. And for the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of tho lawes many ſpiritual me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue reportid openly, &amp; that ſomtyme in open ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch puttyng to anſwer of priſtes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay men is prohibited by the law of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4938:30"/>
god / wherupon me thynketh ar greatly to be noted theſe pointes / that is to ſay, that if it be as they ſay / that it is ayenſt the lawe of god / that than great defaut is in them, that they haue done no more to refourme it than they haue done, for clering the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſo many people, as than daily offend therby. And if it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, as they ſay / than they mainteyn an vntruth, which is a great offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in men of ſuch grauite &amp; ꝑfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they be. And they alſo be therby bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den to reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the temporal princis, which ought to haue theyr fynes &amp; amerciamentes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche ſutes, as ſhulde be taken agaynſt preeſtes in theyr courtes: wherof they or many tymes excluded by reſon of the ſaid pretenſed priuilege. And if it could be ſufficiently proued, that it is ayenſte the law of god, to put priſtes to anſwer before lay men: than degrading of them could nat helpe: For nat withſtandyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſgradyng, the caracter abideth / &amp; ſo he is a preſt ſtyl, as he was before. And I ſuppoſe verily that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kinges ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors wold in time paſt haue aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to it. And that the kyngꝭ grace, &amp; all his
<pb facs="tcp:4938:31"/>
realme, wolde with good wyll alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them ſelf to it / but that was neuer ſufficiently proued, as farre as I haue herde. And to that that ſome ſpyrytuall men ſay, that it is an auncient cuſtome, and a cuſtome approued, that prieſtes in felonies / murthers, &amp; treaſons ſhulde nat be put to aunſwere before laye men, and that by reaſon of that olde cuſtome, they oughte to be pryuyleged in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half / though it can nat be proued direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the lawe of god: to that it maye be anſwered, that there was neuer yet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cuſtom in this realm approued. For prieſtes haue ben arrained alway for tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon and felony before the kynges Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And for treſon it hath ben ſene, that they haue ben put in execution / as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth by a complaynt made by the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in the parlyament holden in the .xxv. yere of kynge Edwarde the thyrde pro Clero / where the clergye complayned, that preſtes, monkes, &amp; religious, were contrarye to the liberties of the churche (as they ſayde) put to dethe: and vppon that complaynt it was enacted, that all maner clerkes, as well ſecular as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4938:31"/>
that ſhulde fro thens forthe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicte before any Iuſtice ſecular, for any maner of treſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or felony / touchyng other perſons / than the kyng or his royal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, ſhulde haue fro thens forthe freely the pryuylege of holye churche, and be withoute lette or delaye delyuered to the ordinarie them demaundyng. And it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that by that terme, Clerke, in that ſtatute pro Clero, is vnderſtond as well clerkes that be within orders, as clerkes that can rede as clerkes, and yet be nat within orders: for they ſhall haue theyr clergy in petyte treaſon / whiche be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menly taken to be ſuche treaſons / as be recited in the later ende of the declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of treaſon, made in the ſayde .xxv. yere of Ed. the .iii. whereof the eſchete belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the lordes of the fee. But in the other treaſons that be recited in the ſayd declaracion / whereof the forfayture is onely to the kynge: none ſhall haue his clergye by the comon lawe / clerke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in orders nor lay man, that can rede / ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>there is nat any remedy prouyded for no maner of clerkes in tho treſons / for they touche the kyng and his royal maieſtie.
<pb facs="tcp:4938:32"/>
And therfore they be excepted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſtatute ꝓ Clero, as before apereth, &amp; be comonly called hygh treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: &amp; of that nature of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is now waſſhyng / clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng &amp; fylyng of money: for the ſtatute made a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no .ii. H. v. is, that it ſhalbe treſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the kynge &amp; to the realme. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no clerk can there haue his clergy.</p>
               <p>¶And here I wolde moue a lytle far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that if a clerke within ordres bren a houſe, bycauſe he hadde nat certayne money layde in a ſecrete place as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by a byll: whether he ſhal haue his pryuylege: for the ſtatute made in that caſe / is that ſuche brennynge ſhall be hyghe treaſon. And yet the forfeiture is gyuen to the lordes of the fee. &amp;c. And the ſayd ſtatute is a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no .viii. H. vi. ca. vi. And ſith it is haute treaſon / many men ſuppoſe, that he ſhall nat haue his cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: but I commytte that to other, that lyſte to treate farther of that matter: But for countrefaytynge and forgyng the coyne of an other realme: I ſuppoſe a clerke ſhuld nat be put in execucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yf he wyll aſke his priuilege. For the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is no more, but that it ſhall be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4938:32"/>
and ſayeth not that it ſhall be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the kynge and to the realme / as the other ſtatute dothe. And therfore I ſuppoſe that by the ſayd ſtatute pro cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro / he ſhal haue his clergy. Yet neuer the leſſe that ſtatute pro clero in one poynte declarethe the common lawe to be more ſtrayter agaynſt the priuilege of clergy / than many men take it to be: and that is in this poynt. If a clerke ſtele any of the kynges goodes, that he ſhall nat haue the priuilege of his clergie. For the ſayd ſtatute is, that he ſhall haue his clergie in treaſon or felony concernynge other perſons than the kynge or his royal ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſty. And therfore for felony co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the kynge ſelfe / it ſemeth that a clerke at the comen lawe, ſhoulde not haue had the priuilege of his clergy: but that I re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myt to other, that be lerned in the lawes of the realme. And I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe matters, becauſe as me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, it were ryght expedient, that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men ſhuld knowe them, &amp; ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as moſt ſpecially ꝑteine vnto them, more parfytely than they haue done in tyme paſte: and more rather to coueyte
<pb facs="tcp:4938:33"/>
to haue the true vnderſtondyng of them, than to reporte that the makers of them offended in the makyng, ſpecially ſeyng that they were made by the kynge, with the aſſent of all the lordes ſpyrytual and temporalle / and of the commens, and ſome of them at the ſpecyall requeſt and peticion of the ſpiritualtie.</p>
               <p>¶And here me thynketh I myght ſaye a lyttell farther in this matter, and that (as it is lyke) the trouth wyll proue, that is to ſaye: that as longe as the iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſpirituall and temporall be ſuffred to ſtande in ſuche caſe as they do nowe, that temporall men ſhall ſay that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men make lawes, that they haue non auctoritie to make / and that ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men ſhall ſay, that temporall men make lawes that be agaynſt the libertie of the churche, wherfore they be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and no other order taken to haue it knowen, what is the libertie of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and what nat / than is yet taken: It wyll be longe ere this dyuyſyon wyll be fully appeaſed. Than to retourne to the pryuyleges of clerkes. The trouthe is, that yet clerkes within orders be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4938:33"/>
more fauoured than clerkes that be not within orders. For if a preeſte be array<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned of felony / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth the felony, or is founde gyltie, and than he prayeth the benyfyte of his pryuylege, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the letters of his orders, in that cas the iudges wyll not compell hym to rede. For ſithe the churche hath admyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hym to orders, the lawe preſumeth that he can rede as many men ſaye. And ouer that if a preeſt wolde wylfully for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his priuilege, and confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felony and become a prouour: yet yf the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narye wyll aſke hym as a membre of the churche / and ſhewe the letters of his orders, he ſhall haue hym, and that is by the ſtatute called articuli cleri. For before that ſtatute he ſhulde haue bene compelled to haue done battayle / yf the approuee wolde haue waged hit. And alſo if a preeſte, after that he hathe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the felony, or after that he is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d gyltie / wyl pray his clergie, and after of wylfulnes he wil renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his priuilege: yet if the ordinarye wyll aſke hym, he ſhal haue hym: and that is by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men lawe. But in this matter hit is a
<pb facs="tcp:4938:34"/>
doubte, to many men / whether it ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to the ordinary only to affirme, that he is a preeſt &amp; ſo to aſke hym: or that he muſt ſhew the letters of his orders. And I ſuppoſe / that it is ſufficient / yf he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that he is within orders, though he ſhewe not the letters of his orders / nor yet the regeſtryng of them. And that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the ſtatute of an .iiii. H. vii. ca, xiii. where it appereth that the Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat of the ordinarye, that he is within orders ſhulde ſuffyce. And if his certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat ſhulde ſuffyce, than it ſemeth that his ſeynge in his owne perſone / that the other is a clerke / ſhulde ſuffyce.</p>
               <p>¶And in the ſtatute made anno .xxiii. Henrici octaui / ca. i. it appereth, that clerkes within holy orders / haue great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter priuilege, concernyng theyr clergie, than clerkes that be not within orders. But neuer the leſſe I leue that matter to the determination of other.</p>
               <p>¶But admytte / that there had ben ſuch accuſtome receyued and admitted in the realme / that preſtes ſhulde not be put to aunſwer before laye men, and that than this queſtyon were aſked, whether the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4938:34"/>
parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t myght breake that cuſtome? To that queſtyon (as it ſemeth) it maye be aunſwered thus: That yf that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome turne in to an occaſyon and bolde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of thefte and murder, and other lyke thynges agaynſt the kynges peace, and that as well in many ſpirytuall men as in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral men by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of ſpiritual me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which by reaſon of that priuilege take a boldnes to offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: It were not only a law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful dede to breke that cuſtom, but a right good &amp; meritorious dede to do it, and a dede that the kynge is bounde to at his coronacion. For he is ſworne to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teigne the good cuſtomes of his realme and to breake the euyll. And ſure it is, that all cuſtomes that be agaynſte his peace / be euyll, as this ſhulde be, yf that effecte ſhulde folowe of it / as before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth. And that the kynge is ſpeciallye bounde by his lawes to aduoyde all thynges, that may be a let to his peace, it apperyth by the ſtatute that is called ſtatutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tione armoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where it is ſayd amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge other thynges thus. To the kyng it apperteyneth by his royall ſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norye to defende ſtrongly all armes, and
<pb facs="tcp:4938:35"/>
all other force agaynſt his peace as ofte as it ſhall pleaſe hym. And that he may punyſſhe them that do againſt his peace after the lawes and cuſtomes of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme. And that al his lordes ſpyrytuall and temporall are bounde to ayde hym therin as theyr ſoueraigne lorde. And ſyth murders and felonyes are ſpecially agaynſt the kynges peace: therfore the ſaid cuſtome ſhuld be againſt his peace / yf ſuche effecte ſhulde folowe of it, as be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore appereth. Wherfore it ſemeth, that he ſhuld than haue auctorytie in his par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyamente to breake that cuſtome, as a thynge agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace and quyetenes of his people. And he that hath auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to aduoyde ſuche thynges, as breake his peace, hath alſo auctoryte to preuent and deuoyde ſuche thynges, as maye gyue occaſion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breking of his peace, as that cuſtome ſhulde do, yf the ſayde effecte ſhulde folowe of it. And certayne hit is, that it hurtethe no more a good preſte, that an euyl preeſte is puniſſhed, than it hurteth a lay man, that he is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed: ne no more than it hurtethe a good lay man or woman, that an nother
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4938:35"/>
is euyll and is punyſſhed for it. And I ſuppoſe verily, that this diuiſion wil ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer be perfytely appeaſed, tylle preeſtes and religious wyl be as lothe to here of any defaute in a lay man or lay woman / as in a preſte or in a relygious perſon. And that wyll neuer be as longe as the great confederacies and ſingularite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth amonge preſtes and amonge re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligious perſons, as it dothe now. The good lay men and women muſt pacient<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beare the euyll reporte of other laye men and women, that be of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dycyon as they be / and ſo they ſhall be taught by ſpiritual me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that they ought to do: but they wyl not do ſo them ſelfe. In ſo moche that I ſuppoſe veryly, that many a preeſt &amp; religious wold grudge more ayenſte an euyll reporte made of a preſt or religious / that in dede were gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in pryde / couetyſe, angre / malice, glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tony, lecherye, or ſuche other: than they wolde be ayenſt a lyke euyl report made of a laye manne or a laye woman, that were not gyltie.</p>
               <p>¶Dyuers other lawes there be / that be made by the churche: that many menne
<pb facs="tcp:4938:36"/>
thynke the churche hadde no power to make: As it is / that no benefice ſhalbe let to a lay man / but a ſpiritual man be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with hym: Or that it ſhall not be let aboue .iii. yeres. And alſo the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of a dimiſſion noble, &amp; ſuche other, that were to longe to reherſe nowe. For theſe ſuffiſe to ſhew, that by ſuch lawes, made by the churche / that they hadde no power to make any lawe of / hath ryſen one ſpeciall cauſe of this diuiſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other occaſion of this diuiſion. The .xiii. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N other occaſion of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion hath ryſen by reaſon of feyned viſitacions, vſed in tymes paſte by ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and other, that haue hadde power to viſyte howſes of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and churches in the countrey: For there is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men opinion in maner vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally ryſen amonge the people, that ſuche viſitacions / after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner as they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4938:36"/>
be vſed / do litel good, and rather encrece vice than vertue. And verilie the more pytie is, it ſemeth to be true as they ſey. For it is vſed / that at ſuche viſitacions, viſitours take of the houſes of religyon that they vyſite / ſomme certeyne pency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And for viſitacion of churches they haue of ſome certayne churche / mete and drynke, where they viſite / and than they gather ſomme certayne duetie of all the churches within a certeyn circute i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that contrey. And neuer the les / as the comen opynyon gothe / comenlye they reforme nothynge / but as they fynde it, ſo they leue it / and neyther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte they vertue / ne punyſſhe vice / but many tymes the contrarie, by ſome worldlie demeanour or euyll example, that the people ſee in them. And thus when the people haue ſene, that offenders, as well ſpiritual as temporall / contynue after the viſitacion as they dydde before: they haue coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured / that the ordinaries and viſitours do viſite more rather for theyr pencions / than for any good order or reformacion. And this / through a longe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:4938:37"/>
hath brought the people to iudge great couetice in ſuch viſitours / whiche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menly be of the greatteſt reulers of the ſpiritualtie: wherby the peole by lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell and lytell haue fallen into a diſpray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of ſuch viſitations / and into a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lykynge of theyr rulers ſpiritual, and of ſuche pompe and worldly behauour, as is ſhewed by them at ſuche viſitations. And than whan ſuch viſitours and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall rulers haue perceyued, that the people haue miſliked theyr viſitations, they haue diſdayned it, and haue conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſtyl as they dyd before: and ſo hath the grudge betwene them contynued ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cretely of long tyme. And ſurely it is to be moche meruayled, that viſitours wil attempte to take at theyr viſitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s any penſion or impoſition of them that they viſite, contrarye to the good lawes that be made in the .vi. boke, ti. de cenſibus. ca. romana, et exigit. Wherin great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties be ſet vppon them that take any penſion at theyr viſitations / contrary to the ſayd lawes / as in the ſame doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere. And but there be any ſecret diſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſation in that behalfe: many be ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4938:37"/>
/ that dayly miniſtre. And if there be any ſuche ſecrete diſpenſation, hit is to doute, that the graunte therof proceded not of charite, but of ſome couetyſe and ſingularite: yf the very grounde therof were throughly ſerched. Wherfore hit were ryght expedient / that ſuche viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were ſet in ſuche order, as well by ſpirituall auctoritie / as by temporal auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toritie, that good men hereafter myght therby be comforted / and euyll men cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected &amp; reformed, to the good example of all other that ſhulde here of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other cauſe of this dyuyſion. The .xiiii. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N nother cauſe of the ſayd diuiſion hathe ryſen by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the greate multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of lycences and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſations, that haue benne made for money by popes and buſſhops in tyme paſte / contrary to dyuers good lawes made by the churche, as of plura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lites, ayenſt the law that no man ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:4938:38"/>
haue but one benefice / and of lycence to curates to be non reſident, of capacities to men of religyon, and that none ſhall take orders ne be promoted afore a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne age, and ſuche other: whiche ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences &amp; diſpenſacions haue bene ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomably graunted for money with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe reaſonable, that great inconue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyences haue folowed vppon it, to the great grudge, and murmour, and euyll example of all the people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An other cauſe of the ſayde dyuyſion. The .xv. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N other occaſyon of the ſayde diuiſyon hathe ryſen by a greate larnes and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye of lyuynge / that the people haue ſene in many religious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For they ſay, that though religious men profeſſe obedience &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty / yet many of them haue &amp; wil haue theyr owne wil, with pleynty &amp; delicate fedynge, in ſuch abundance that no obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience nor pouertie appereth in them.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4938:38"/>
And therfore many haue ſayde, and yet ſay to this day, that religious men haue the moſt pleſant &amp; delicate lyfe that any men haue. And truly if we behold the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes &amp; bleſſed exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of holy fathers, &amp; of many religious perſons, that haue bene i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme paſt / and of many religious perſons that be now in theſe dayes: we ſhulde ſe ryght great diuerſity bytwene them, I trowe (as for many of them) as greate diuerſitie as is bytwene heuen &amp; hell. And here, as it ſemeth, I myght conuenyently reherſe the wordes that be ſpoken in the fyrſt boke of the folowyng of Chryſte / the .xviii. chapiter, where it ſpeaketh of the holy fathers, that haue bene in religion in tyme paſt / and ſayth thus. They ſerued our lorde, in hunger and in thurſte, in hete and in colde, in na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes / in labour, and in werynes / in vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giles &amp; faſtinges, in prayers, and in ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye meditations, in perſecucions, and in many reproffes. They refuſed honours here in this lyfe, that they myght alway haue them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſtyng lyfe. O how ſtrayt and howe abiect a lyfe led the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers in wyldernes? howe greuous
<pb facs="tcp:4938:39"/>
temptacions they ſuffered? howe fyerſly they were with theyr gooſtly ennemyes aſſayled? howe feruent prayer they day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered to god? what rygorous abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence they vſed? howe great zele &amp; fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour they had to ſpiritual profyte? how ſtronge batayle agaynſt all ſynne? And howe pure and holle entent they hadde to god in al theyr dedes? on the day they laboured, and on the nyght they prayed. And though they laboured on the daye bodily, yet they prayed in mynde, and ſo they ſpent theyr tyme alway frutefully, and thought euery houre ſhorte: for the ſeruyce of god / and for the great ſwete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that they hadde in heuenly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, they forgette ofte tymes theyr bodily refection. All ryches / honour / di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnities / kinneſmen, and frendes they re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounced for the loue of god. They coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to haue nothynge of the worlde, ſo that ſkarcely they wolde take that was neceſſarye for the bodily kynde. They were poore in worldly goodes / but they were ryche in grace and vertues. They were nedy outwardely, but inwardely they were replenyſſhed with grace and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4938:39"/>
gooſtly comfortes. To the worlde they were alyens and ſtraungers, but to god they were ryghte deere and familyar frendes. In the ſyght of the worlde and in theyr owne ſighte they were vile and abiecte, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of god and of his ſaynctes they were precious and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly electe. In them ſhone al perfection of vertue / trewe mekenes, ſymple obedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, charitie, and pacience / with other like vertues &amp; gracious gyftes of god. Wherfore they profited dayly in ſpirite, and opteyned great grace of god. They be lefte as an exaumple to all religious perſones, and more oughte theyr exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to ſtere them to deuocion, and to profite more &amp; more in vertue &amp; grace / than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great multitude of diſſolute and ydle perſones ſhulde any thynge drawe them abacke. O what feruoure was in religious perſons at the begynnyng of theyr religion? What deuocion in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / what zele to vertue, what loue to gooſtly diſcipline, and what reuerence and meke obedience flouryſſhed in them vnder the rule of theyr ſuperiour? true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theyr dedes yet bere witnes / that they
<pb facs="tcp:4938:40"/>
were holy and perfyte, that ſo myghtly ſubdued the worlde / and thruſt it vnder fote. Thus farre gothe the ſayde chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But the more pitie is / moſt men ſay, that nowe a dayes many religious men wyl rather folow theyr owne wyl, than the wylle of theyr ſuperiour, and that they wylle neyther haue hunger nother thyrſt, heate, nor colde: nakednes, wery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / nor labour, but riches, honor / digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, &amp; worldly acqueinta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſeruantes at their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, pleaſures / diſportes, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more lybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally than temporal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue. Thus are they fallen (ſay they) fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherby the deuocion of the people is in maner falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Neuertheles I dout not / but there be many right good &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous religious perſons, god forbede it ſhulde be otherwyſe: but hit is ſayde, that there be many euyll, and that in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che multitude / that they that be good canne not, or wyll not, ſee them refour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And one great cauſe that lettethe reformation in this behalfe is, this: If the moſte diſſolute perſone in all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minaltie / and that lyueth moſt openly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4938:40"/>
ayenſt the rules of the religion, can vſe this policye, to extolle his relygion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other / and diſprayſe other rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, for that they be not of ſuche perfection as theyr relygion is, anone he ſhall be called a good ſeruente bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / and one that beareth vppe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygion, and ſhall be therfore the more lyghtely forborne in his offences.</p>
               <p>Where the throuthe is, that the religion maynteyneth hym, and bearethe vppe hym / and not he the religion. For hit hathe lyttell nede of hym. And thoughe many be good and lyue a ryghte good and laudable lyfe, after the ſtatutes and order there vſed: yet in that poynt / to extolle theyr religyon aboue other, and to take parte with them, that doo ſo thoughe they knowe: that they that ſo extol it / kepe not the religion them ſelfe, fewe be without offence, and truly that is a great defaute, for it gyueth a great boldnes to offenders / and diſcourageth theym, that be good / whanne they ſee them that moſte lyue ayenſte theyr rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, be ſo maynteygned and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4938:41"/>¶An other thyng that hath cauſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people to miſlike religion, hath bene the great extremyte, that hath ben many tymes ſene at elections of abbotes, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and ſuche other ſoueraygnes ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall. And this is a generall grounde, that whan religious men perceyue / that the people myſlike them / they in theyr hartes withdrawe theyr fauour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocion agayne fro them: And ſo hathe charitie waxed colde bytwene them.</p>
               <p>And veryly I ſuppoſe / that hit were better, that there ſhulde no abbotte or pryoure hereafter contynue ouer cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne yeres, that ſhuld be appoynted by auctoritie of the rulers, than to haue ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che extremites at elections, as hath bene vſed in tyme paſte in many places.</p>
               <p>¶And veryly (as me ſemeth) one thyng wolde do great good concernynge reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and all religious perſones, and that is this: that the reules and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions of religion were ſene and wel con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered / whether the rygour and ſtrayt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of them may be borne nowe in theſe dayes, as they were at the begynnyg of the religions. For the people be nowe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4938:41"/>
more weyke, as to the multitude / than they were than. And yf it be tought / that they maye not be nowe kepte: that than ſuch relaxacions and interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theyr rules be made, as ſhall be thought by the reulers expedient: For bettre it is to haue an eſye rule wel kept than a ſtrayte rule broken without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: For therof foloweth a boldenes to offende / a quyet herte in a euyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: a cuſtome in ſynne, with many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll examples vnto the people: wherby many haue found defaut at al religion, where they ſhulde rather haue founde defaute at dyuers abuſions agaynſt the true religion: for certayne it is, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions were firſt made by holy fathers, by the inſtincte of the holy ghoſte, kepe them who ſo may.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The concluſyon of this lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell treatiſe. The .xvi. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4938:42"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ythe there is no ſacrifyce that more pleaſeth almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty god / than zele of ſoules dothe / it is good that euery man diſpoſe hym ſelfe, as nyghe as he can / to haue that zele: And if he may through grace come thervnto, it ſhall inſtructe hym in many thynges, how he ſhal behaue him ſelfe anenſte his neyghbour. And fyrſte hit ſhall teache hym / that he ſhall take hede, that he do nothynge / that myght gyue occaſion vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his neyghbour to offende. And I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde nat therby, that he ſhall onely take hede, that he do none euyll dede, wherby his neyghboure maye take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to offende, whiche in latyn is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led offendiculum / that is to ſay / an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to offende: but I meane alſo, that he ſhall take hede / that his neyghboure take none occaſion to offende by no dede that he ſhall do, thoughe it be good, as gyuyng of almes, or buyldynge of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or ſuche other: which if the people iuged to be done of pryde &amp; vaine glory / muſt be lefte for a tyme, for hurtynge of them that be of that opinion: tyll they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4938:42"/>
maye be inſtructed of the intente of the dede. And yf they wyll in no wyſe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed, than bycauſe hit ſemeth to be of malice, as was in the phariſeys: their iudgement may be diſpyſed / &amp; the good dede contynued.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo where trouth ſhulde peryſſhe / if the good dede ſhulde be omytted / there a good dede is not to be omytted. And accordynge to that is ſayde before / the bleſſed apoſtell ſaynt Paule, of a great zele that he had to the people / ſayde:</p>
               <p>¶If eatynge of fleſſhe ſhulde hurt my neyghbour, I wolde neuer eate fleſſhe. And therfore in the ſayd chapiter he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed all them, that wolde eate mete, that was offered to ydolles before them that were newly conuerted of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles / and that were yet but weke in the faythe: that they ſhulde beware, that though they knewe, that they myghte lawfully do as they dydde, that yet they ſhulde take hede, that theyr brother were not offended therby. And in all that chapiter the holy apoſtell treateth moch that it is good to euery man to be ware / that through his dede he gyue no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:4938:43"/>
to his brother to offende. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche almyghty god, that euery manne, but mooſt ſpecially our lordes and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſpirituall, may hereafter endeuor them ſelfe to kepe wel this poynt, that is to ſay / that they do nothyng to gyue the people occaſion to offende: and ouer that, that they may diligently inſtructe the vnlerned people to the knowlege of the trouthe / and to ſtable them as well by doctrine as by good example / al ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularite ſette aparte. And for as moche as doctrine and good example perteyne moſte ſpecially to prelates and ſpiritual rulers, therfore I ſhall brefely recyte cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne auctorities / that ſhall ſome what moue them to haue a zele and loue vnto the people. And alſo to be pyteous vnto them: And for ſhortenes I ſhall omytte for this tyme to ſhewe by whome the ſaid auctorities were ſpoken, beſechyng the reders to take heede to the wordes that be ſpoken, though hit appere not who ſpeake them.</p>
               <p>¶Firſt I fynde diuers auctorities that ſay thus: It is expedient, that prelates ſtudy more to profite the people, than to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4938:43"/>
haue preeminence ouer the people.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo I fynde wrytten / that thoughe puniſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may not holly be omytted, that yet it profyteth moche / that it be ſomtyme deferred.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that it behoueth neceſſarily, that he that hath rule ouer other, brenne euer in a quycke lyuely zele to the helthe of theyr ſoules, that he hath rule of: And that els he ſhal lyttel profyte vnto them. And therfore he coueteth vndiſcretly to haue rule ouer them, that he ſtudyeth not to profyte vnto. And therfore this is ſayde ſpecially to prelates and to other that haue rule ouer the people: Rule ye to forſee the perylles and daungers of them that ye haue rule of / to counſaylle them to procure theyr helth, and to ſerue and to profyte to other / as good faythful and wyſe ſeruauntes, whome our lorde hath ordeyned ouer his houſeholde.</p>
               <p>Plante ye vertue in them by holſomme doctrine / water it by good example, and helpe them with your prayour / and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ye done that perteineth to you, and our lorde ſhal well gyue encrece of gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge / whan hit ſhall pleaſe hym / and
<pb facs="tcp:4938:44"/>
that parauenture there as after mannes iugement was farre vnlyke. Theſe thre thynges therfore be very neceſſary, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne, example / and prayour, but the greatteſt of them is prayour. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſayd to the prelates thus: Knowe ye, that ye oughte to be as mothers to the people, and not as lordes / and ye ought to ſtudye rather to be beloued tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dred, and if it be neceſſary ſome tyme to haue correction, that it be a fatherly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and not as it were of a tyraunte / and ſhow your ſelfe as mothers in noriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge of the people / and as fathers in correctyng them. Be meke / put away al fierſenes / forbere betyng / &amp; ſpeke vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people faire &amp; ſobre wordes, and ſet not your yock to greuouſly vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe burdeyns ye ought rather to bere. If ye be ſpiritual, inſtruct y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of Softenes, &amp; let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre hym ſelfe well, leeſt that he may be alſo tempted. He that is a mother dyſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muleth not / he can ioye with them that ioye / wepe with them that wepe / and he wylle not ceaſſe to thruſte oute of the breſte of compaſſion the mylke of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4938:44"/>
He taketh hede, if he can perceyue any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that is vexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any great temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion or trouble / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is heuy &amp; weike therwith: And if he finde any ſuch, with him he ſoroweth, him louingly he entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, him he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth, &amp; findeth anon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of pitie &amp; truſt, wherwith he reſſeth him vp ayen to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of ſpirit And yf he knowe any that is prompte / quick, &amp; wel profityng i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace / he ioyeth with hym, he giueth hym many holſome cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes, &amp; kindeleth him / and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hym all that he can to perceuer and profyte euer fro better to better, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth him ſelfe to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he torneth the effections of al men vnto him ſelfe in al goodnes, and proueth him ſelfe verily to be a mother, as well of them that be offenders, as of them that profiteth in grace: And as a trewe leche he ſeketh as well them that be ſycke as theym that be hoole / and all this he dothe through the gyfte of pitie, and of a zele, that he hath to the helth of theyr ſoules. Alſo a good diligence ſhepeherde neuer ceſſethe to fede his flocke with good leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and exaumples, and that with his
<pb facs="tcp:4938:45"/>
owne example rather than with other mens, For yf he fede them with other mens examples, and not with his own / hit is but a rebuke vnto hym, and his flocke ſhal not profyte moche therby.</p>
               <p>For if a prelate wyll ſhew vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the ſobrenes of Moiſes, the pacience of Iob, the mercy of Samuell, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes of Dauyd, &amp; ſuch other examples of bleſſed men: and he hym ſelfe be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meke, vnpacient, vnmercyfull, and not holy, it is to fere, that al thoſe examples ſhal lytel profyte. And therfore prelates, that in tyme paſſed haue bene the verye trewe ſhepeherdes, though they hadde theyr bodyes here of the erthe, yet neuer the leſſe they fed the flockes of our lorde to them commytted with heuenly fode, and vſed not to preache to them theyr owne wyll, but the wylle of god. And one man ſaythe of prelates this: Whan I (ſaythe he) beholde the heyght of the honour of prelacy, forthe with I drede the peryll and daunger of it. And whan I conſidre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degree, I drede the ruine. I conſidre the heyghte of the dignitie / and I beholde forthwith the mouthe of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4938:45"/>
Helle open euen at hande. For there is no doubt, but that theyr adminiſtracion is more perillous, than is the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of any other. But yet neuertheleſſe yf they adminiſtre wel, they ſhal get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe therby an hyghe degree in heuen / &amp; they ſhal receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gretter abundance &amp; more ful meaſure of peace for their good trauaylle for euer. And I beſeche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty god to ſende theſe .iiii. thynges habundantly in to the worlde, and that moſte ſpecially amonge prelates, and ſpirituell reulers, that is to ſaye / zele of ſoules, pitie / good doctrine, and deuout prayour. And than vndoubtedly, a new lyghte of grace, and of Tractabilitye, ſhall ſhortely ſhewe and ſhyne amonge the people.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth this Treatyſe concernynge the diuiſion betwene the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtie &amp; the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraltie.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4938:46"/>
            <head>TABVLA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſte that the dyuyſyon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge ſpyrituall men them ſelfe hath bene one cauſe of the diuyſyon / that is nowe bytwene the ſpyrytualtye &amp; temporalty in this realme.</p>
            <list>
               <label>The firſte Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That the omyttynge of dyuers good lawes / with certaine defautes and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in men of the church / whiche among other be recited and declared by Iohn Gerſon: haue bene an other occaſion of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The ſeconde Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That certayne lawes made by the churche, wherin it is recited, quod laici ſunt clericis infeſti, that is to ſaye, that laye men be cruell to clerkes: hath bene an other cauſe of this dyuyſion.</item>
               <label>The thyrde Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That the extreme lawes made by the church for leyenge violent handes vpon clerkes / haue bene an other cauſe of this dyuyſyon.</item>
               <label>The fourth Chapiter.</label>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4938:46"/>¶That the diſorderynge of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſentence / hath bene an other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of the ſayde diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The fyfte Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That an other occaſion of this diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath partly ryſen by temporal men, through diſordrynge of theyr chapleyns and chauntrye preeſtes.</item>
               <label>The ſyxte Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That ſutes taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes (ex officio) haue ben an nother occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The ſeuenth Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That though after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> determination of doctours / a man is not an heretyke, for that only that he erreth, but for that he opinatyfely defendeth his errour, and that neuer the leſſe the ſpiritualtie, as a commen voyce gothe amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, haue in tyme paſte punyſſhed many for hereſie vpon lyght cauſes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherupon many people haue grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged / and that grudge hath ben an other occaſyon of this diuyſion.</item>
               <label>The eyght Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That the parcialite that hath benne ſhewed vpon ſutes taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirituall
<pb facs="tcp:4938:47"/>
courte by ſpirituall men, hathe bene an other cauſe of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The nynthe Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That the extreme and couetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour of ſome curates with theyr paryſſhens, hath ben an other cauſe of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The tenthe Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That the grauntyng of pardons for money, as it were to ſome charitable vſe, that hath not after folowed, hathe rayſed an other grudge amonge the people, whiche hath ben an other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The leuenth Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That the makynge of lawes by the churche, whiche they hadde none auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie to make / hathe bene an other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The twelthe Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That lacke of good viſitacions, hath bene an other occaſion of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The thyrtene Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great multitude of lycences and diſpenſacions made by ſpiritual ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers for money vpon lyght ſuggeſtions hath ben an other cauſe of this diuiſion.</item>
               <label>The fourtene Chapiter.</label>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4938:47"/>¶That the great laxnes and worldely pleaſures of religious perſons / wherby the people hath benne greatly offended / hath bene an other occaſion of this diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion.</item>
               <label>The fyftetene Chapiter.</label>
               <item>¶Than for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion of this treatiſe it is ſom what touched, howe good it is to haue a zele of ſoules, and howe peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous it is to do any thynge / wherby they myght be hurted. And that if zele of ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, pitie, good doctrine, &amp; deuoute pray our / were abundauntly in this worlde, mooſt ſpecially in prelates &amp; ſpirituall rulers: that than a newe lyght of grace and tractabilite, wolde ſhortely ſhewe and ſhyne amonge the people.</item>
               <label>The .xvi. Chapiter.</label>
               <item> </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynted at London in Flete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrete next vnto ſayncte Dunſtones churche, by Robert Redman.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
